Welcome to another edition
ようこそいらっしゃいました！
今月の新しいJW Broadcastingです
of JW Broadcasting!
This month we will see examples
今回は 王国を第一にしている
世界中の若い人たちに注目しましょう
of what young ones
around the world
have done to seek
the Kingdom first.
Also,
また 若い時にいろいろな問題を
経験した 一人の兄弟をご紹介します
you will meet a brother
who got into a lot of trouble
early in his life.
But how did the truth help him
どうやって 真理の助けで生き方を
変えたでしょうか？楽しみですね
to straighten out his life?
We look forward to his story.
そして エクアドルの言語訓練コース
の様子も見ましょう
We will also visit
a language course in Ecuador.
What is it like
to learn a new language
新しい言語を学んで宣教を拡大するとは
いったいどういうものでしょうか？
to expand our ministry?
We will find out.
探ってみましょう
それでは 3月のJW Broadcating
スタートです！
This is the March program
of JW Broadcasting!
My theme for this month’s broadcast is
今月のブロードキャストの主題は—
“若い皆さん エホバと共に
将来を築きましょう！”です
“Young Ones
—Build Your Future With Jehovah!”
If you do,
1 Timothy 6:19 assures
そうするなら
テモテ第一 6章19節にある通り—
that you will
‘safely treasure up for yourself
“自分のため 将来に対する
りっぱな土台を安全に蓄え—”
a fine foundation for the future,’
and you will
“get a firm hold on the real life.”
“真の命をしっかりとらえる”ことに
なるでしょう
Obviously, we will be directing
many of our comments
もちろん わたしたちはこの話を—
エホバの組織にいる愛する若い皆さんに
直接語りかけたいと思っています
directly to you dear young ones
in Jehovah’s organization.
Yet, if we think about it,
でも 考えてみると—
all of us figuratively
わたしたちが生きたいと願っている
永遠という時間と比べると—
are very young ones
compared to eternity
わたしたちは皆
比喩的に言って若者です
—how long we hope to live.
So, in a sense,
our comments during this broadcast
ですから ある意味で—
このブロードキャストで話されることは
わたしたち皆に当てはまります
have application to all of us.
Personally, I am so thankful to Jehovah
高校卒業後すぐに
開拓奉仕をするようにとの—
積極的な仲間の圧力があったことを—
that positive peer pressure
was put on me
わたしは個人的に
エホバに感謝しています
to enter the pioneer ministry
right out of high school.
What a blessing and a protection
それはわたしにとって祝福であり
保護になりました
it was to enter
the regular pioneer work
17歳で正規開拓奉仕を始め—
at age 17
18歳でベテルに行くことが
できたのです
and to be able to go to Bethel at 18.
Even though there was considerable
worldly pressure put on me
大学教育を追い求めるようにとの—
周囲からのかなりの圧力が
ありましたが—
to pursue university education,
I am so happy that with Jehovah’s help,
エホバの助けのおかげで—
エホバと共に将来を築くという決定が
できたのは大きな喜びです
I decided to build my future
with Jehovah.
Truly, I have no regrets.
わたしは何も後悔していません
And this is always true of young ones
心からエホバに仕えている若者たちも
同様に感じています
who serve Jehovah from their hearts
—they have no regrets.
後悔などはしていません
In fact, you will enjoy
these expressions from young ones
それでは エホバと共に将来を築いている
若者たちの声をお聞きください
who are building
their future with Jehovah.
Before I started pioneering,
開拓を始める前は 毎月
時間が入るか不安でした
I was really nervous that I wouldn’t be able
to get my time in every month.
It was a bit hard when I started pioneering
because I didn’t have a car.
車がなかったから
始めるのはちょっと大変でした
My boss,
he didn’t give me part-time work.
上司はパートを
認めてくれませんでした
I found it really hard
to balance schoolwork
学校と開拓の両立は大変でした
and pioneering
at the same time.
My biggest struggle was fear of man,
so that really hindered me
一番の障害は人への恐れでした
人と話すのが苦手だったからです
because I wasn’t very good
at talking to people.
Having a good routine was a struggle.
良い習慣を持つのに苦労しました
My brother and I are
the only ones in the truth.
真理にいるのは兄とわたしだけです
My family didn’t understand
なんで奉仕に行きたいのか
家族に理解してもらえませんでした
why we wanted to go preaching.
I didn’t think
that I’d make a good pioneer.
できるとは思えませんでした
I’ve had Type 1 diabetes
since I was five.
5歳の時からⅠ型の糖尿病なので—
So I was always worried
about whether or not
健康と開拓のバランスが取れるか
いつも心配でした
I could balance that health condition
with pioneering.
The challenges
don’t seem that big now,
今と比べて以前は
もっと問題が大きかったんです
but back at that time
they were a really big deal.
エホバの助けが すご過ぎです
But the coolest thing
was how Jehovah helped me.
Prayer to Jehovah
helped me overcome my fears.
祈って恐れを克服しました
My family was
a massive help from Jehovah.
家族はエホバからの強力な助けです
Because my dad was the one
who first encouraged me to pioneer,
開拓を最初に励ましてくれたのは父です
when I did start pioneering,
he promised that I would have
家族からのフルサポートを
約束してくれました
the full support of my family.
When I spoke to brothers and sisters
who spent their youth
若いときに全時間奉仕をした
兄弟姉妹と話すことが—
in the full-time service
that really helped me
大きな助けになりました
because it was really encouraging,
and it really motivated me
すごく力をもらって—
わたしも全時間奉仕を経験したい
っていう気持ちになりました
to want to make my own memories
and my own experiences
in the full-time service.
So there were
practical things I could do.
できることをしました
車がないから 歩くかバスに乗りました
I didn’t have a car;
I just walked or I caught the bus.
I had to work out
what my priorities were first.
優先順位を決めました
So I had to find out how many hours
would I have to go witnessing every week.
毎週 何時間奉仕すべきか考えました
それから 曜日ごとに いつ奉仕して
いつ学校に行くか計画を立てました
So then I just sat down
and I looked at every day
and planned out which days
I could go witnessing,
which days I had to go to school,
宿題とか研究する時間も
取れるようにしました
and also allocated time
so that I could do my homework and study.
Having a schedule
was really good
予定を立ててよかったです
because I could see it
all out in front of me,
やることを全部書きだしてみたら—
and I could see
that the hour requirement
要求時間を達成できるって分かって
無理って思わなくなりました
was actually attainable,
so that made it a lot less daunting.
I first set short-term goals of pioneering
in the special months of activity.
初めは 特別活動の月に
開拓をする短期的な目標を持ちました
Then I was able
to begin continuous auxiliary,
それから 連続で補助をして
最終的に正規開拓を始めました
and then eventually
I started regular pioneering.
One of the best things I did
to prepare myself for pioneering
すごくよかった開拓の準備は
補助開拓です
was to auxiliary pioneer beforehand.
開拓をしながら
直面するどんな困難も—
It really set me up
to be able to overcome
克服できるよう準備できました
any challenges
that I faced while I was pioneering.
I thought about Malachi 3:10.
マラキ 3章10節を考えました
I knew I trusted in Jehovah,
エホバを信頼していたけど
試みるいい機会でした
but this was my chance
to test him out.
I prayed,
put my trust in Jehovah,
祈って エホバを信頼し
申し込みました
and put my application in.
After my form
was in for pioneering,
開拓者になってしばらくして
ある兄弟が仕事をくれました
a brother, with time,
a brother called me and offered me work.
I had unemployment
for three months,
3か月仕事がなかったから大変でした
which wasn’t a good time.
でも その間に
エホバに注意を集中しました
But during that time,
I had Jehovah as my main focus.
エホバは支えてくださって
見捨てたりされませんでした
And so he supported me,
and he didn’t let me down.
Asking brothers and sisters to come
奉仕する人が少ない日に—
and work with me,
maybe on days that I knew
兄弟姉妹に一緒に働くよう
お願いしました
that I wouldn’t get as much support,
really helped.
すごく助けになりました
That helped me to organize
my hours a little bit more,
もっと時間を活用できるし
兄弟姉妹をよく知ることもできます
and also I’d get to know
my brothers and sisters more as well.
One of the greatest joys of pioneering
has been to pioneer with Mum.
すごく嬉しいのは
母と開拓ができることです
And we had the privilege of going
同じ開拓者学校に行けて
とてもよかったです
to the pioneer school together,
which was really special.
Psalm 16:8 reminds me
詩編 16編8節からエホバが
すぐそばにいてくださると分かります
that Jehovah is right beside me.
When I’m preaching,
it’s like Jehovah is holding my hand.
奉仕のとき
手を握ってくださっているみたいです
So with full-time service,
I love making Jehovah happy.
全時間奉仕をして
エホバを喜ばせたいです
与えられたものすべてを用いて
やっと少しお返しできます
With everything that he has given me,
I’m finally able to give something back.
Looking back
—pioneering—
振り返れば
開拓は今までで最善の決定です
it was the best decision
I’ve ever made.
It’s opened up
so many different avenues
エホバへのいろんな
奉仕の道が開かれます
of service to Jehovah,
また 全時間奉仕を続ける
真の願いを持つ助けにもなります
and it helped me also
to have that real desire
to want to stay
in full-time service.
Helping someone
on the road to everlasting life,
道行く人を永遠の命へ導くのは
最高です
it’s the best feeling ever;
and it’s really irreplaceable.
何にも代えられません
The only thing I can say,
勧めたいことはただ1つ—
“As a young person, start pioneering!”
“若いうちに 開拓奉仕！”
What a fine attitude
those young ones have!
何と立派な態度ではないでしょうか？
They are clearly following
in Jesus’ footsteps.
この若者たちは
イエスのあとに従っています
Jesus was the wisest man
イエスは地上で最も賢い人でした
who ever walked the earth.
He could’ve pursued any career
どんな職業にも優れた能力を
発揮できたでしょう
and truly excelled at it.
He could’ve been
the greatest carpenter who ever lived.
世界で最高の大工になれたはずです
Think about it,
イエスは父を助けて
物質の宇宙を造りました
he helped his Father
build the physical universe.
Can you imagine
what kind of houses he could’ve built?
どんな家を建てることができたか
想像できますか？
Or what if he had pursued
being an inventor?
発明家になっていたら
どうでしょうか？
With his perfect brain,
完全な頭脳を使って—
he probably could’ve invented
the telephone,
電話や車やコンピューターを
西暦1世紀に発明できたことでしょう
automobile, or computer
in the first century.
Or what about becoming
a businessman?
ビジネスマンになっていたら
どうでしょう？
With perfect intelligence,
he likely could’ve come out on top
完璧な知性を使って—
自分がかかわった
あらゆる商業取引から利益を上げ—
of every business transaction
that he entered,
becoming the richest businessman
who ever lived.
世界一の大富豪になることが
できたでしょう
Or have you ever thought about
あるいは運動選手になっていたら
どうだったか考えたことがありますか？
if he had pursued becoming
an athlete?
And excelling in athletic contests
イエスの時代 運動競技で勝つためには
大きな努力が求められました
was a huge endeavor in Jesus’ day.
With a little training,
it is likely that his perfect body
完全な体を持つイエスは
ほんのわずかな訓練で—
would have outperformed all people
不完全な体を持つ—
他のすべての選手よりも
優れたパフォーマンスをして—
with imperfect bodies,
enabling him to become
世界で最も優れた運動選手に
なったことでしょう
the most famous athlete who ever lived.
Or one more example,
もう一つの例です
what if he had decided to become a doctor?
イエスが医者になっていたら
どうでしょう？
He could cure sick people
病気の人を癒し—
死者を生き返らせることも
できたでしょう
—even raise the dead.
Can you imagine how much
he could’ve charged rich people
人を生き返らせるとどれくらいの料金を
お金持ちから請求できたと思いますか？
to raise their dead loved ones?
でも イエスは
このいずれをも追い求めませんでした
But Jesus pursued none of these careers.
Why?
なぜですか？
Because he knew
that any of such endeavors
それは イエスがこのいずれもが—
would have only very limited
非常に限られた一時的な益しか
もたらさないことを知っていたからです
and temporary benefits.
Instead, he pursued something
代わりに イエスはより多くの人に
永続的な益をもたらすもの—
he knew would bring far-reaching
and everlasting benefits:
つまり全時間宣教を追い求めました
the full-time ministry.
If this is how the wisest man
who ever walked the earth—
地上で最も賢い人が推論して
そう結論したのであれば—
If this is how he reasoned,
わたしたちも同じように考えて
賢い者であることを示せるでしょう
we are wise if we strive to think
the same way.
That makes me think of the comments
以前 巡回奉仕をしていた時に会った—
of a well-adjusted teenage brother
良く訓練された十代の兄弟の
語ったことを思い出しました
whom we served
while in the circuit work many years ago.
This young brother went straight into
the regular pioneer work
この若い兄弟は 高校卒業後すぐに
正規開拓奉仕を始めました
out of high school,
and I asked him why he did so.
わたしはなぜそうしたのか
聞いてみました
He explained that he knew
he could’ve gotten a full-time secular job
兄弟が言うには—
and bought a new car for himself,
全時間の仕事について
自分で新車を買うこともできるけれど—
but he reasoned that in a few years
数年もたてば車はさびてダメになるし—
that car would rust out and break down,
そうしたら何も残らなくなるって
考えたそうです
and he would have nothing.
But he knew that he could go
into the pioneer work
でも 兄弟は開拓奉仕を始めて
エホバとの近しい関係を築き—
and build a close relationship
with Jehovah
and perhaps even find
an honest-hearted person
心の正直な人々を見つけて—
真理を教えることができるかもしれない
ことを知っていました
and be able to teach that one the truth.
And he knew that would last forever.
そして それが永続する益をもたらす
ことを知っていたのです
Now, that is some wise thinking
この若い兄弟がそう考えたのは
賢明なことです
on the part of that young brother.
And today, that brother
has a beautiful Christian wife
この兄弟には
美しいクリスチャンの妻と—
幾人かの霊的な子どもたちがおり—
and several spiritual children,
いま兄弟は立派な長老として
奉仕しています
and he is serving as a fine elder.
But if you young ones
are going to think this way
でも若い皆さん このように考え
霊的な目標を追い求めたいなら—
and continue to pursue spiritual goals,
it is vital that you wisely choose
自分の友を賢く選ぶことは大切です
your associates.
In a sense, our associates
ある意味 友はエレベーターに
例えることができます
can be likened to an elevator.
What do we mean?
どういう意味でしょう？
Well, they can take you up
あなたを引き上げたり
引き降ろしたりするということです
or they can take you down.
If you choose wisely,
賢明に選ぶなら
引き上げてくれます
they will take you up
—elevate your good qualities
良い特質を伸ばし
より良い人にならせてくれます
and make you a better person.
But if you choose poorly,
でも まずい選択をすると
引き降ろされるのです
they will take you down.
Depending on how badly you choose,
選択がどれほどまずいかによって—
they can take you way down
地下室まで—
—to the basement,
場合によっては—
even the subbasement.
地下2階にまで
引きずり降ろされてしまいます
箴言13章20節で—
At Proverbs 13:20,
わたしたちを造られた愛ある天の父は
その点をこう説明されました
our loving heavenly Father,
who made us,
explains how it works.
エホバはこう述べておられます
Jehovah tells us there:
“The one walking with the wise
“賢い者たちと共に歩んでいる者は
賢くなり—”
“will become wise,
“but the one
who has dealings with the stupid
“愚鈍な者たちと交渉を持つ者は
苦しい目に遭う”
will fare badly.”
“Walking with”
“共に歩む”とか“交渉を持つ”とは
“友になる”と言う意味です
and “having dealings with”
mean “associating with.”
And who are the “stupid” ones?
では“愚鈍な者”とはだれですか？
Well, this scripture contrasts
such a person
この聖句はそのような人を
賢い人と対比しています
with those who are wise.
It is not talking about someone
who lacks mental intellect.
それは勉強ができない人のことでは
ありません
It is talking about someone
それはエホバの基準からして—
who does not make
wise decisions spiritually
霊的に賢い決定をしない人のことを
述べているのです
from Jehovah’s standpoint.
そう考えると—
And if we think about it,
少なくとも 今のこの時に
エホバに仕えようとしていない人は—
anyone who is not really serving Jehovah
だれであれ 全く賢い人ではありません
—at least right now—
that one is unwise indeed.
そしてそのような人たちと
いつも一緒にいるなら—
And if we associate closely with such ones,
エホバは“苦しい目に遭う”と
述べておられます
Jehovah says that we “will fare badly.”
別の例えを考えてみましょう
We could use another illustration.
Think about someone who is physically sick
病気にかかっていて
高熱のある人がいるとします
and is running a high fever.
If we spend a lot of time with that person,
その人と長い時間共に過ごすなら
同じ病気にかかってしまうことでしょう
we will probably catch the same sickness.
Or worse,
もっと悪いことに—
if we spend a lot of time
near a dead body—a corpse—
死んだ人つまり死体のそばに
長時間いるなら—
we will probably pick up a disease.
病気に感染することでしょう
Well, it is similar
霊的に病気の人 さらに悪いことに
霊的に死んでいる人と—
with spending time with a person
who is spiritually sick,
時間を過ごすことについても
同じことが言えます
or worse, spiritually dead.
On the other hand,
if we choose as our associates
一方 エホバを愛し エホバと共に—
those who love Jehovah
永遠の将来を築こうとしている人々を
友として選ぶなら—
and who are building
their everlasting future with Jehovah,
わたしたちは
大いに益を受けることができます
we will benefit greatly.
Please observe carefully
this variety of young ones
エホバと共に忙しく
天に宝を蓄えている—
次の様々な若者たちのことを
どうぞ注意深くご覧ください
who are busy storing up
treasures in heaven
with Jehovah.
How heartwarming it is to us
これらのりっぱな若者たちが—
—and we know it is to Jehovah—
イエスの次の勧めを
実践しているのを見るのは—
to see these beautiful young people
わたしたちにとって
心温まるものですが—
doing what Jesus encourages
それはエホバにとってもそうでしょう
at Matthew 6:20, 21.
それはマタイ 6章20, 21節
の言葉です
There, Jesus encourages:
イエスはこう言われました
“Store up for yourselves
treasures in heaven,
“自分のために天に宝を蓄えなさい”
“そこでは蛾もさびも食わず”
“where neither moth nor rust consumes,
“盗人が押し入って
盗むこともありません”
“and where thieves do not break in and steal.
“あなたの宝のある所
そこにあなたの心もあるのです”
“For where your treasure is,
there your heart will be also.”
And if we think about it,
色々考えてきましたが
結局のところ—
in the final analysis,
老若を問わず わたしたちの真価は—
after all is said and done,
whether we are younger or older,
エホバと共に何を天に蓄えたか
ということになります
our net worth will be
what we have stored up
in heaven with Jehovah.
We will not be able to take
material treasures with us
物質の宝を持って
大患難を通過することはできません
through the great tribulation.
And if we die,
死んでしまうなら
物質の宝を持って行くことなどできません
we certainly will not be able to take
material treasures with us,
しかし 霊的な宝は
大患難を通過するときも
but we can take spiritual treasures
with us through the great tribulation
死と復活を経験したとしても
携えて行くことができます
and even through death and resurrection.
It is true with all of Jehovah’s people,
啓示 14章13節は—
as it is with the anointed,
油そそがれた者についても
すべてのエホバの民にも当てはまります
what is stated at Revelation 14:13.
そこには “彼らの行なったことは
そのまま彼らに伴って行く”とあります
It says there:
“The things they did go right with them.”
And how encouraging it is
若い皆さんがバプテスマを受けるのを
見ると 本当に大きな励みになります
to see young ones getting baptized
—publicly demonstrating
それは自分の命をエホバにささげたことを
公に示すことです
that they are giving their lives to Jehovah.
And we sincerely hope
まだバプテスマを受けていない
若い皆さんが資格をとらえたならすぐ—
that you young ones
who are not yet baptized
will not hold back from getting baptized
バプテスマを受けることを
ちゅうちょしないように—
心からお勧めしたいと思います
as soon as you qualify.
The sooner you can get baptized,
バプテスマを早く受ければ
それだけ早く—
the sooner you will receive
greater protection
エホバからの大きな保護と祝福を
受けることができるのです
and blessings from Jehovah.
Not long ago,
it made me very happy
それほど昔のことではありませんが—
10歳のかわいい兄弟がバプテスマを
受けたのを見てとてもうれしく思いました
to observe a little ten-year-old brother
get baptized!
And young ones,
若い皆さん
自分がエホバの証人であることを—
never be afraid to identify yourselves
明らかにすることを
決して恐れないでください
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Never allow the fear
of what others may think
ほかの人がどう思うかと恐れて
自分のことを隠してはなりません
to cause you to hesitate to do so.
Jehovah tells us
エホバは箴言 29章25節で
こう述べておられます
at Proverbs 29:25:
“Trembling at men is a snare,
“人に対するおののきは わなとなる”
“しかし エホバに依り頼んでいる者は
保護される“
“but the one trusting in Jehovah
will be protected.”
Many years ago when I was in school,
ずっと昔 学校にいたころのことですが—
I can remember being
at times somewhat worried
時々クラスメイトは自分のことを
どう思っているのだろうかと—
about how my fellow classmates
would view me.
不安な気持ちになったことがありました
But then a little while later,
でも それから少したって
卒業しましたが—
I got out of school
and never ever again even saw
わたしは以前のクラスメートのほとんどに
一度も会ったことがありません
most of those former classmates.
Then it dawned on me
それで気づいたのですが—
人が自分の事をどう思うかは
本当は重要ではないのです
that it doesn’t really matter
what people think about us.
It is Jehovah’s rating of us
エホバがどう思われるかが重要なのです
that truly counts.
Humans cannot add
人間は寿命を5秒たりとも
延ばすことはできませんが—
even five seconds to our lifespan,
but Jehovah can add
エホバは永遠を人に与えたり
取り去ったりできるのです
or subtract eternity.
エホバだけが
真の幸福を与えることができる方です
And he alone
can also give us true happiness.
And as Proverbs 29:25 indicates,
箴言 29章25節が
示しているように—
what a protection
it is to courageously identify ourselves
勇気をもって自分がエホバの証人で
あることを明らかにし—
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバを全く信頼して
エホバにしっかり付くなら—
fully trusting Jehovah
and taking our stand solidly with him.
それはわたしたちにとって
素晴らしい保護となります
Never be ashamed of who you are.
自分がだれであるかを
決して恥じてはなりません
You are one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
あなたはエホバの証人なのです
And please, dear young ones,
愛する若い皆さん
we warmly encourage you
皆さんを愛している人たちの
言うことを聞いてください
to listen to those who love you.
エホバ神は皆さんを愛しています
Jehovah loves you very much;
the Governing Body loves you very much;
統治体も皆さんを愛しています
the elders love you very much;
長老たちもそうです
your Christian parents love you very much.
クリスチャンの親たちもそうです
And these ones will tell you the truth,
これらの人たちは
あなたに真理を語ります
even though at times
あなたが聞きたくないと
思うようなことも語ります
it may not be what you want to hear.
They will not ‘tickle your ears,’
これらの人たちは—
あなたの“耳をくすぐる”ようなことは
言いません
perhaps like ones at school
or in the neighborhood
本当はあなたを愛しておらず
あなたの最善を願っていない—
who don’t really love you
学校の友達や近所の人たちとは
違うのです
or have your best interests at heart.
But please believe those
でも あなたを愛しているからこそ—
who will tell you the truth
あなたに真理を語る
これらの人たちを信じてください
because they love you.
And never view
Jehovah’s laws and principles
そして エホバの律法や原則のために—
何か良いものを得損なっている
とは決して思わないでください
as depriving you of something good.
View them as protecting you
それはあなたを傷つけるものから
あなたを守っているのです
from what will hurt you.
If you recall,
思い出してください
Satan convinced Eve
サタンは
エホバが制限を設けているために—
that she was being deprived by Jehovah
何か良いものを得損なっていると
エバに思い込ませました
and was missing out on something good.
Now, it is true that Eve
was missing out on something.
エバが何かを得損なっていたのは
本当です
But what was she really missing out on?
でも実際には
何を得損なっていたでしょうか？
A tormented conscience,
良心の呵責に苦しむこと—
her beautiful hair turning gray,
美しい髪が白髪になること—
her teeth falling out,
歯が抜け落ちること—
her perfect skin wrinkling up like a prune,
もち肌に深いしわが生じること—
being bent over from old age,
年と共に腰が曲がること—
hobbling around on a cane,
杖をついてよぼよぼになること—
and finally dying!
最後に死を迎えることです
But Satan convinced her
サタンはエホバが何かを奪っていると
エバに思い込ませました
that Jehovah was depriving her,
so foolishly she reached out to get
愚かにも—
エバはいわば自分が得損なっていると
思ったものを得るようになったのです
what she thought she was missing out on.
Well, Satan will try to use
サタンはあなたにも同様の策略を
用いようとするでしょう
the same kind of strategy on you,
but please don’t let him do it!
でも決してそうさせてはなりません
This also makes me think
of an experience a brother once related.
先ほどお話しした兄弟の経験を
思い起こします
He said that he was visiting
an animal observatory,
兄弟によると
ある動物観察施設に行った時のこと—
and a large lion lunged toward him
大きなライオンが
兄弟に向かって突進してきました
but was prevented from reaching him
でも 動物とその施設を隔てていた
分厚いガラスのおかげで—
by a thick glass pane
separating the animals from the observers.
ライオンは来ることができませんでした
As the lion stood on his hind legs,
ライオンは後ろ脚で立ちあがり
爪でガラスをひっかき—
clawing the glass
大きな牙をむき出していました
and baring his massive teeth,
the brother came to realize in a special way
兄弟はその保護バリアのありがたさを
特別な仕方で実感しました
the protective value of that barrier.
Previously, he said
that he somewhat viewed the glass pane
兄弟によると ガラスに汚れが
ついていると良く見えないので—
as a restriction
それまでは そのガラスの塀は
余計なものと見ていました
because the smudges on it
partially blurred his view,
but now he viewed it
でも 今では本当に保護するものだと
みなすようになりました
as a real protection.
Well, in a similar way,
同様にサタンは—
Jehovah doesn’t want Satan,
ペテロ第一 5章8節で—
who is described
as ‘a roaring, devouring lion’
“ほえて歩き回る”ライオン
として描かれています
at 1 Peter 5:8—
それでエホバは若い人たちがサタンに
むさぼり食われるようなことを—
He doesn’t want him
to gobble down you young ones.
願ってはおられません
And His laws and principles
エホバの律法と原則は
皆さんを守るためのものなのです
are designed to keep that
from happening to you.
So please listen to Jehovah.
どうか エホバの言われることを
聞いてください
He loves you!
エホバはあなたを愛しておられます
You would probably agree
that having good friends
良い友と一緒にいると
勇気がわいてくると思いませんか？
is of great encouragement
in your service to Jehovah.
エホバのために奉仕し続けよう
という気持ちになります
You may also recognize
でも気づいていると思いますが—
that there is more
to being a friend
良い友を見つけて友情を育てたいなら—
than simply clicking links
on a computer screen
パソコンとかスマホのSNSとかを
使って—
or a smartphone.
知り合えばよい というわけ
ではありません
But where can you find
good friends
では 良い友がなかなか見つからない—
when there seems to be
no one to choose from?
そう感じるとき
どうしたらよいでしょうか？
In this dramatization,
consider the example
of this young brother
次のドラマを見ましょう
そのことを考えている
若い兄弟が登場します
who struggled
with this very question.
My name is Akil.
名前はアキル
When I was 18,
my family moved to a new city.
18の時 家族で引っ越した
It was bad enough
leaving my friends behind.
友達と別れるのは辛かった
But now,
それに 新しくできるかも分からない
I wasn’t sure
if I could make new ones.
My parents seemed really happy.
両親はとても幸せそう
だから心配をかけたくない
I didn’t want
to make them feel bad
僕の気持ちを話すと
がっかりするだろうから
by telling them how I really felt.
The new school
wasn’t much better
学校は退屈だった
until I met Cameron.
キャメロンに会うまでは
He seemed
like a pretty cool guy.
いい奴そうだな
Soon, his friends
became my friends.
すぐに 友達が増えた
…ダビデの信頼は心からのもので—
. . . something that David
believed was true,
he actually proved it
by the association that he kept.
彼が保った友情がそれを証ししています
We think about one
of the closest friendships
ダビデとヨナタンの友情関係について—
recorded in the Scriptures,
聖書から考えてみましょう
and it was
that of David and Jonathan.
What was it that David and Jonathan
shared in common?
2人の友情は何に基づいていましたか？
年齢でしょうか？
It wasn’t their age.
アキル 集会中メールしてたわね
Akil,
you were texting in the meeting.
I shouldn’t have sent the text.
分かってる ごめん
I’m sorry.
But Cameron is a good person.
でも キャメロンはいい奴なんだ
He might even study one day.
いつか研究するかも
I understand that, Akil.
気持ちは分かるよ
But we all have to be careful
with how much time
でも エホバを愛さない人と
いつも一緒にいることには注意しないと
we spend with people
that don’t love Jehovah.
See,
their values are just different.
持ってる基準が違うね
You know
what Proverbs 13:20 says:
箴言 13章20節が言うように
“賢い者たちと共に歩”むんだ
‘Walk with those who are wise.’
So why don’t you seek out
friends who love Jehovah?
エホバを愛する友達を探してごらん
And you will make friends
that last a lifetime.
ずっと続く友達が見つかるよ
How am I supposed to do that?
どうやってできるの？
会衆に同い年なんていないよ
There’s no one my age
in the congregation.
親友は思いがけないところにいるものよ
Akil, good friends
can come from unexpected places.
Mom,
I had good friends
親友は…いたよ
—back home.
前にね
We all felt bad that night.
その夜はたくさん話し合った
The next day,
次の日 キャメロンが
パーティーの写真を見せてくれた
Cameron posted pictures
of a party he had.
My parents were right.
両親は正しかった
I broke off my association
with Cameron
キャメロン達と付き合うのはやめた
and his friends,
but I still felt
でも また独りぼっちだ
lost.
Hi, Akil?
アキル
土曜日だれかと奉仕する？
Do you have
field service plans for Saturday?
Ah, no.
ああ いえ
そう なら9時半に集合場所で
いいかい？
Good.
Now you do.
I’ll see you
at the 9:30 a.m. meeting, OK?
After service,
奉仕の後
マックス兄弟が家に招いてくれた
Max had the group
over for refreshments.
Did you take these?
兄弟これ……？
Do you like them?
気に入った？
Yeah.
ええ
My wife,
she was always the photographer.
妻が いつもカメラ持って—
She loved photography.
熱中していたんだ
And then one anniversary
she went out and bought me a camera,
で 結婚記念日に カメラをくれたんだ
and from that moment on,
I was hooked too.
それから わたしもとりこだよ
Time flies so quickly.
ほんとに早い
It’s hard to believe
she passed away 12 years ago now.
妻が亡くなってもう
12年も過ぎたとはね
I’m sorry.
そうですね
It’s OK.
まあね
But you still take pictures?
でも…今でも写真を？
I do.
I really enjoy photography.
ああ
撮るのは楽しいよ
There’s something about being close
特に相手は エホバの創造物だ
to Jehovah’s creation.
It reminds me
そんな時—
独りぼっちじゃないって感じるんだ
that we’re never really alone,
you know?
どう？
Good friends can come
from unexpected places
親友は思いがけないところにいる
年が違っても
and unexpected ages.
As I spent more time with Max,
兄弟と知り合うにつれて 分かったんだ
I realized it was
just like David and Jonathan.
ダビデとヨナタンみたいだ
2人の友情の基盤は—
Their friendship was based,
年齢じゃなく エホバへの愛だった
not on age,
but on their love for Jehovah.
そして お互いに支え合った
And they helped each other.
マックス兄弟の助けで—
And with Max’s help,
今も良い霊的な習慣を
続けることができている
I was able to keep
a good spiritual routine
without interruption.
Although we weren’t the same age,
年が違っても 兄弟と親友になれた
Max became my good friend.
目を向ければよかったんだ
I just needed to see
what was right
目の前にある正しいことに
in front of me.
Yes, friends can come in various ages.
年が離れていても 友になれます！
And the best kind of friend
本当の友 それは エホバに
仕え続けるよう強めてくれる人です
is one who encourages us
in our service to Jehovah.
We all need to work hard
on making spiritual progress
霊的に成長するとは エホバ—
また エホバの性格をもっと
よく知るということです
—learning new things
about Jehovah and his qualities.
So we want friends
who will help us do that.
その努力を支えてくれる
本当の友に出会いたいですね
There is a saying
ことわざで “経験は最良の教師”
と言われることがあります
that experience
is the best teacher,
but that is not
really accurate.
でもそれは違います
Experience is often
the hard way to learn.
つらい経験をして 苦しんで
教訓を学ぶことになります
Brother Fernando Casillas
was born in Mexico,
フェルナンド･カシージャス兄弟は
メキシコで生まれました
but when he was a baby,
小さい時 家族でアメリカに
引っ越すことになります
his family moved
to the United States.
The neighborhood he grew up in
兄弟は ギャングの影響力が大きい
地域で成長しました
had a lot of gang influence.
This had
a very negative impact on him.
若い時の経験がもとで 兄弟は人格面で
大きな問題を抱えるようになりました
But despite these circumstances,
いったいどうやって真理に
引き寄せられたのでしょうか？
notice how the truth attracted him.
見てみましょう
I used to love violence;
I dreamed of violence.
暴力を愛していました
暴力の夢さえ見ました
My gang was my religion.
ギャングはわたしの宗教でした
I got into the prison system
at a young age.
若い時から
矯正施設のお世話になりました
At first, they sent me
to a juvenile facility,
最初 少年の施設に入れられて—
but I got kicked out of there
for a riot.
Basically, they deemed me a threat
to the safety and security
暴動を起こしたかどで
そこから出されました
わたしは施設にとっても—
of the institution,
the guards, and other inmates.
看守や受刑者にとっても
危険人物とみなされたので—
And I was sent
to solitary confinement
残りの刑期を終えるまで
独房に入れられました
to finish off my prison term.
Me thinking
I was violent back then
刑務所を出てきたときには—
was nothing compared to
what I came out with.
以前にも増して
暴力的になっていました
Basically,
what you try to come out to be
世界一の殺し屋になってやろうと
思いました
is the best killer out of all.
After my incarceration,
刑期が終わると
メキシコに国外追放になりました
I was deported to Mexico.
I used to carry a weapon
with me everywhere I went.
いつも武器を携帯しました
After a while, we started getting involved
with bad people.
そのうち
悪い仲間と付き合うようになり—
ガールフレンドも
トラブルに巻き込んでしまいました
Eventually,
my girlfriend got in trouble.
Once that was over,
事が収まった後
彼女が王国会館を見つけました
she saw a Kingdom Hall.
My girlfriend had been
to meetings as a child,
彼女は子どもの頃
集会に行っていたので—
so she basically dragged me
to the Kingdom Hall.
今度はわたしも
引っ張ってゆかれました
They treated me nice.
歓迎されました
And that’s when I started
to get to know Omar.
オマルと彼の奥さんと
知り合いになりました
So I started hanging around
with him and his wife
それから 彼らとの付き合いが始まり
集会にも行くようになりました
—me and my girlfriend at the time—
and going to meetings.
ところが オマルが以前
ライバルのギャングだったことを知った時—
But it wasn’t till I found out
this guy
used to be one of my rivals
怒りがこみ上げてきました
—I was very, very upset.
自分から話してくれなかったからです
I felt betrayed because he never told me.
Everything that was going
through my head was,
あの時は
“どうやってあいつを連れ出して—”
‘I’ve got to find a way to get him over here,
“仕返ししてやるか”
ということばかり考えました
so I can hurt him.’
After thinking about all the things
that I wanted to do to him that night
オマルにどんな仕打ちをするか
一晩中 考えて—
—I’d been running it through my head
over and over again—
結局 このまま友達でいることに
したんです
I decided to just stay friends with him.
And eventually,
we decided to start studying together.
その後 オマルと研究を始めました
Being the way I was,
I thought that there’s
昔の自分を 神が許して下さるわけがない
と思っていました
no way a God can forgive me.
The scripture at Isaiah 55:7
really helped me,
でも イザヤ 55章7節は
本当に助けになりました
where it says:
“Let the wicked man leave his way
and the evil man his thoughts;
“邪悪な者はその道を—”
“害を加えようとする者は
その考えを捨て—”
let him return to Jehovah,
who will have mercy on him.”
“エホバのもとに帰れ”
“神はその者を憐れんでくださる”
As time went by,
I started understanding clearly
学んでゆくにつれ エホバが本当に
許して下さることが理解できました
that Jehovah does forgive.
By that time, I had already
kind of made a decision
that I was done
with doing time in prison.
その頃には もう刑務所に戻るようなことは
しない決意でいました
I just decided to cut all ties with everybody
that had anything to do
with anything illegal.
違法なことをする人たちとの
どんな付き合いも断つ決意でした
I felt like a free person.
And after progressing
自由になったと感じました
and quitting the habits that I had
of smoking and drinking a lot,
タバコも大酒もやめて—
進歩して伝道者になりました
I became
an unbaptized publisher.
But my father passed away;
でも 父が亡くなって
また悪い友達と付き合いはじめ—
I started hanging around
with bad association again,
伝道者を削除になりました
and eventually
I had my privileges removed.
And as that was happening,
Satan attacked me again.
サタンはそういう時を
すかさず突いてきました
So one day,
my wife was crossing the border
ある日 妻が書類作成のために
国境を通過しようとした時—
to go take care of
some paperwork for the kids
車の中に麻薬があると言って
警備員に止められました
and was surprised
by the border patrol
telling her that there
were drugs in the vehicle.
車の以前の持ち主が隠していたんです
We did not know
that the previous owner
had stashed drugs in the truck.
知る由もありませんでした
Even though later they proved
後になって妻の嫌疑が晴れてからも—
that the drugs were not my wife’s
and she was released,
子どもたちは帰してもらえませんでした
they still decided to keep my kids.
What I was thinking of doing
was going back to my old ways
昔のやり方に戻るところでした
昔の仲間に頼んで
子どもたちをメキシコに連れ戻すのです
—organizing a plot with my old friends
to bring my kids
back to Mexico to me.
でも この度はエホバに
そして兄弟たちにも頼ることにしました
But I decided to rely
on Jehovah instead
and on the brothers
coming to visit me
on a regular basis
兄弟たちは
定期的に訪問してくださり—
and giving me encouraging thoughts
エホバの保護に頼るよう
励まし続けてくださいました
of how Jehovah
will take care of everything.
Eventually, our kids were returned to us,
エホバの助けで
子どもたちは帰してもらえました
with Jehovah’s help.
After a little struggle,
of course, I had my privileges back.
努力のいることでしたが
再び伝道者になり—
A few months later, I was baptized.
数か月後には
バプテスマを受けました
I’m a lot happier now
than what I was back then.
昔の自分よりずっと幸せです
One day as I was preaching
in the rehab centers,
リハビリセンターで伝道した時には—
I ran into a person
I once knew before, growing up.
子どもの頃 見たことのある人に
出会いました
わたしが誰であるかが分かると
その人は言いました—
Once he found out who I was, he said:
“You’re the reason why I left town.
“あんたのせいで おれは引っ越したんだよ”
Every time you would see me,
you would shoot at me.”
“おれを見ると いつも銃で撃ってきた”
So after a while,
I was able to convince him
ちょっと時間がかかりましたが—
that actually my purpose there
傷つけるためではなく真理を教え—
was not to hurt him anymore
永遠の命を得る方法を
伝えるために来た—
but to teach him the truth
ということを納得してもらえました
and how to gain everlasting life.
I’m no longer a violent person.
もう暴力的な人間ではありません
I enjoy the privileges
that Jehovah now gives me.
エホバから特別な割り当てもいただいています
I have now been serving
as a ministerial servant
奉仕の僕として2年間仕えています
for the past two years.
I’m in charge of the accounting
会計の奉仕もしていて—
for the Kingdom Hall,
昔の自分だったら
盗んでいたお金を扱っています
instead of stealing money
as I used to do before.
What I do for a living
is I do gardening work.
園芸で生計を立てています
Now I don’t carry around knives,
今はナイフではなく
園芸道具を持ち歩いています
but I carry around my tools.
You could say that I did beat
ピストルをすきの刃に
もしくは芝刈り機に打ち変えたわけです
my pistols into plowshares now
—or weed whacker or lawn mower.
I’m glad that I’m
now serving a great God
偉大な神にお仕えできて幸福です
who is loving,
caring, and forgiving.
愛と気遣いの神
許して下さる方にです
Fernando and his family
are serving
フェルナンド兄弟は 家族と一緒に—
in an English congregation in Mexico.
メキシコにある英語会衆で
奉仕しています
With everything
Brother Casillas went through,
兄弟は自分の経験から—
“最良の教師”は経験ではなく
エホバだと悟りました
he could see
that Jehovah is the best teacher.
If you listen to Jehovah,
エホバに従ってください
you won’t have to learn
the hard way.
つらい経験を背負って
苦しむ必要はありません
Jehovah is
エホバはあなたのためを思い—
“the One teaching you
to benefit yourself.”
あなたの“益”になることを
教えているのです
Jeremiah 17:13
conveys the thought
改訂版のエレミヤ 17章13節
を見ると分かりますが—
that those
who do not serve Jehovah
エホバに仕えようとしない人たちの名は
塵の中に書かれていることになります
will have their names
“written in the dust.”
But by building
your future with Jehovah,
若い皆さん エホバと共に
将来を築いていってください
you young ones are ensuring
that Jehovah will keep
your individual names
そうするなら
エホバは皆さんの名前を—
written in his “book of life”
フィリピ 4章3節と
啓示 3章5節で述べられている—
that is mentioned
at Philippians 4:3
“命の書”に書き留めてくださいます
and Revelation 3:5.
Earlier in the program,
このプログラムの最初のほうで—
we saw some examples
of how young ones
エホバと共に将来を築いている
若い人たちが出てきました
are building a future
with Jehovah.
そのような若い人たちの努力は—
But what impact are such efforts
having on the organization?
エホバの組織にどんな良い影響を
与えているでしょうか？
Let’s look at one example:
一つの例を見ましょう
the construction
of the new world headquarters
ニューヨーク州ウォーウィック世界本部
の建設の様子です
at Warwick, New York.
Jehovah’s Witnesses built
1.6 million square feet (149,000 sq m)
エホバの証人は4年足らずで—
14万9000平方メートルの
建物を建てました
in less than four years.
2万7035人の自発奉仕者のうち
3247人は19歳から25歳でした
Of the 27,035 volunteers,
3,247 were between the ages of 19 and 25.
I thought this was a project
経験を積んだベテランの兄弟姉妹だけを
必要とするプロジェクトだと思っていました
that was going to strictly need
very experienced brothers and sisters.
Early on, I realized I was wrong.
でも すぐにそれは間違いだと
気づきました
It was also going to take youthful energy
仕事量が多いので 若い力が
どうしても必要でした
because of the volume of work.
The mix of older and younger ones
年長者と若者が交じってウォーウィック
のプロジェクトを助けてくれました
was really a helpful thing
on the Warwick project.
The older ones
brought skill and experience.
年長者は技術と経験があります
The younger ones
brought the energy, the muscle,
若者にはエネルギーや体力 また
粘り強く行なう勤勉さがあります
and the diligence to stay
with hard physical tasks
all the way through the project.
Whether it was in the kitchen
or night watch
キッチンや夜の警備の仕事もあれば—
朝5時に マイナス12度の中で
コンクリートを打つ仕事もあります
or the early 5:00 a.m. start
with the concrete crew
at 10 degrees Fahrenheit (-12°C),
their joy and their humility was outstanding
どの仕事も謙遜に 喜んで行なう姿は
際立っていました
to accept any work that needed to be done.
And a lot of young ones,
brothers and sisters,
若い兄弟姉妹が大勢
通いの奉仕のために移動して来ました
moved into the area
so they could commute.
And they would work
day after day tirelessly,
いつも精力的に働き 晩になっても元気で
次の日の工程に間に合いました
into the evenings even,
to have the project ready for the next day.
Their energy was just astonishing.
そのパワーに圧倒されます
Jehovah loves young ones,
and he’s willing to invest in them
エホバは若者を愛しておられます
喜んで彼らに投資し 訓練し
組織の一員になるのをお望みなのです
and train them and make them
a part of his organization.
And I saw that so much.
それを何度も見てきました
高い技術を差し出す若者が大勢います
We had a lot of young people
who offered themselves
with technical skills.
But if the humility of these
very technically-skilled young people
しかし たとえ専門技術があっても—
能力以上に 謙遜さがないと
エホバは用いることはされないでしょう
didn’t match
or exceed their abilities,
then, really,
Jehovah couldn’t use them.
And they were willing to adjust,
and we really saw the benefit.
彼らは進んで調整しました
その益を実際見てきました
We knew and they knew
これは単なるウォーウィックの建設
プロジェクトではなく—
that they were building
エホバのため霊的に建てるプロジェクト
であることを—
not just a project at Warwick
わたしたちも若い奉仕者たちも
分かりました
—they were building
a spiritual project for Jehovah.
You could see Jehovah’s spirit
operating on them.
エホバの霊が彼らに働いているのが
分かります
You could see them
mature so quickly.
あっという間に円熟するんです
These young brothers
are the next generation
こうした若い兄弟たちは次世代の長老や
旅行する監督になります
of elders
and traveling overseers.
They’re to be commended
and highly respected
ここでの貢献は高く評価され
称賛されるものです
for the contribution
they made as young men.
They all talk about the effect
彼らはベテル奉仕がもたらした良い影響
についてよく語っています
that their Bethel service
has had on their outlook
and how they don’t want
to get caught up
またこの世の日常の事柄に気を
散らされたくないとも言っています
in this world
and its daily pursuits.
Use the skills you’ve learned
このプロジェクトやベテルで学んだ
技術を使ってください
here on this project and in Bethel.
You are needed.
皆さんが必要なのです
Continue to keep your spirituality up
高い霊性を保ち 築き上げる交わりを
持ってください
and to keep your association
at a high level.
The highest quality of life is when,
最も価値ある人生とは—
偉大な陶器師エホバの手に
自分をゆだねて—
as clay, we put ourselves
in the hands of the Great Potter, Jehovah,
“ここにわたしがおります！わたしを
遣わしてください”と言えることです
and we say:
“Here I am! Send me!”.
確信して言えますが—
And I’m fully confident
they will have no regrets
自分の将来をエホバと共に築くことに
決して後悔はしないでしょう
building their future
with Jehovah.
Yes, young ones
truly had a beautiful impact
若い兄弟姉妹は世界本部の
建設プロジェクトに—
on the construction project
of world headquarters!
本当に大きく貢献してくれました
By the way,
you may find it interesting to know
さて ウォーウィックとウォールキルの
建設プロジェクトについてですが—
that the Warwick
and Wallkill construction projects
実はこのプロジェクトを
進めるための資金は—
were not funded
by the donations
世界的な業のための寄付から賄われた
わけではありません
that you have made
to the worldwide work.
Your donations are being used
to support the work
皆さんの寄付は 世界中の野外の
活動を支えるために用いられています
in the worldwide field.
The massive construction projects
at Warwick and Wallkill
ウォーウィックとウォールキルの
巨大建設プロジェクトは—
were funded by the sale
of properties in Brooklyn.
ブルックリンの資産を売却した
資金で賄われました
In effect,
we just traded locations.
つまり 場所を変えただけ
ということです
We traded the value
of the properties in Brooklyn
ブルックリンの資産を—
ウォーウィック ウォールキルの—
for the beautiful facilities
at Warwick and Wallkill.
この美しい施設に交換した
ということになります
And I must say,
お伝えしておきたいと思いますが—
the Governing Body is truly enjoying
統治体はウォーウィックの新しい本部で
過ごす毎日を本当に楽しんでいます
the new facility at Warwick,
thanks to the hard work,
若い人たちも 年長の人たちも—
both of the young and the older ones
わたしたちのため懸命に
働いてくださいました
who labored in our behalf,
心から感謝しています
and we truly appreciate it.
The apostle Paul said of Timothy
フィリピ 2章20節から23節で—
as recorded
at Philippians 2:20-23:
使徒パウロはテモテについて
こう言いました
“For I have no one else
of a disposition like his
“あなた方のことを真に気づかう—”
“彼のような気持ちの者は
わたしにとってほかにいないのです”
“who will genuinely care
for your concerns.
“ほかの者はみな自分の益を求め—”
“For all the others
are seeking their own interests,
“キリスト･イエスの益を
求めていません”
“しかしあなた方は 彼が自分自身に
ついて実証した事柄を知っています”
“not those of Jesus Christ.
“But you know the proof
he gave of himself,
“つまり 良いたよりを推し進めるため
子供が父親に対するようにして—”
“that like a child with a father
“he slaved with me
to advance the good news.
“わたしと共に奴隷として
仕えてくれたことです”
Therefore,
he is the one I am hoping to send.”
“そのようなわけで わたしはこの人を
遣わしたいと希望しているのです”
It is obvious that Paul
パウロは 若いテモテを
深く愛していました
loved the young man Timothy very much
because of his unselfish hard work
それは テモテが自分のことを
後回しにし—
in behalf of Kingdom interests.
王国のために懸命に働いていたからです
Well, the Governing Body
feels exactly the same way
統治体も 若い兄弟姉妹に対して
同じように感じています
about you dear young ones
who are working hard
皆さんは 与えられたそれぞれの
神権的な責任を懸命に果たしています
in your various theocratic assignments.
In addition to the many avenues
of full-time service
プログラムの最初のほうで見たように
全時間奉仕には—
we mentioned earlier
in the program,
いろいろな分野があります
加えて 地元で生じる必要のため
自分を役立てることも大切な奉仕です
making yourself available
when a need arises locally
is a fine way
to seek the Kingdom first.
そのような奉仕をして
王国を第一に求めることができます
For example, in San Antonio,
in the state of Texas,
例えば 米国テキサス州の
サン･アントニオで—
in the United States,
a large convention
2万人以上が出席する
とても大きな大会が計画されました
with over 20,000
in attendance was planned.
However,
the venue could only provide
しかし 会場から提供された
椅子の数は—
about one third of the chairs needed
for the convention.
出席者の3分の1ほどしか
ありませんでした
Where would our brothers
find the needed chairs?
兄弟たちはどうやって椅子を
確保したでしょうか？
Well, Jehovah provided,
そこには エホバの助け—
and many young ones
were eager to help.
そして たくさんの若い人たちの
働きがありました
When I heard
that this needed to happen,
必要が知らされた時
どうしたらいいんだろうと思いました
I was thinking,
‘How are we going to do this?’
I thought, ‘It’s a big job!’
圧倒されました！
It was amazing!
びっくりしました！
The first thing I was asked to do
最初に求められたのは—
was try to find a storage place
that we could use
6000から8000脚の椅子の
保管場所を確保することでした
for six to eight thousand chairs.
A sister manages a storage place,
ある姉妹が経営している所で
オーナーが—
and we saw Jehovah’s blessing
“エホバの証人の組織と契約できるなら
1年間無料で使ってよい”と言ったので—
because the owner said,
“You can have this stall
“at no charge for a year
as long as you sign a contract
エホバの祝福を感じました
that it’s
for Jehovah’s Witnesses’ organization.”
Truckload after truckload
after truckload came in.
トラック トラック またトラック
We had to unload the trucks.
椅子を降ろし ひとつずつ分けて修理し
掃除し パレットに重ねて戻し—
The brothers had
to unstack the chairs,
repair the chairs, clean the chairs,
put them back on pallets,
restack them,
またトラックに入れました
load them onto trucks,
and that was half of it.
でも 倉庫に入れたものはまだ半分です
Those were the ones
in the warehouse.
On the other side,
we got permission to ask
加えて サン・アントニオにある会衆に
椅子を貸してくれるよう依頼しました
the San Antonio congregations
if we could use their chairs
for the convention.
3000脚の椅子です
We were hoping
to get three thousand chairs.
And then the numbers
grew for the audience,
大会の規模が大きくなったので
もっと椅子が必要です
so we had to increase
our numbers.
それでサン･アントニオ周辺の会衆から—
So we were able to gather
six thousand chairs
6000脚を自発奉仕者の手によって
集めることができました
from the willing volunteers
of congregations around San Antonio.
これについて祈り 奉仕者が募られ
最初から大きな協力が得られました
So we prayed about it and the brothers
started asking for volunteers,
and it was a great cooperation
right at the beginning.
As soon as
we let the friends know
兄弟姉妹たちにこの件について話すと
すぐにみんなが—
that this was going
to be the case,
“仕事を早引きして手伝います”
と言いました
all of them—
all of them said,
“We’re going to get off
of work early.”
すぐに自分たちの予定を調整しました
We immediately wanted
to clear our schedules
so that we could be available
to help in any way that we could.
できることは何でもしたかったからです
It was a privilege to know
わたしたちの会衆が一端を担えたのは
貴重な機会でした
that our congregation
was going to be part of it.
We are so grateful to Jehovah
that he has given us
大切なチャンスを与えてくださった
エホバに感謝しています
this privilege to do.
We had thousands of chairs
いろんなカラーの椅子がありました
緑 赤 ブラウン 青—
of every color
—green, red, brown, blue.
We even had some bright orange ones
left out of the ‘70’s,
オレンジ色の椅子も70脚ほどあり
全て運びました
and we’re putting those in the back.
But it was not just the colors
but the sizes.
でも問題はサイズです
They were all different sizes.
みんな違っていました
And so how do you make
sections with straight rows
どうやってきれいに並べるかが
課題でした
when the chairs
are all different sizes?
But I knew somehow,
as Jehovah’s people, we’d get it done.
でも エホバの民としてできる
と思いました
And we definitely—
As you see, a lot of volunteers,
多くの奉仕者が集まりました
そして成し遂げたのです
and we’re here getting it done.
初めて会う兄弟姉妹たちと友情を
深められたのは 素晴らしいことです
And it’s made
for a beautiful experience
because the friends have gotten to know
each other as never before.
And they’re willingly
working together,
皆が一致して働く意欲に満ちていました
and the excitement is there.
It doesn’t matter whose venue it is,
it’s all for Jehovah,
会場を使うかどうかにかかわらず
すべての人がエホバのために働きました
and that’s been
the attitude everybody has had.
It just tells you
that Jehovah is a God of order.
確かにエホバは秩序の神です
It’s good to feel
that you’re doing your best for Jehovah.
エホバにベストを差し出せて 満足です
詩編 127編1節に—
Well, it reminds me of Psalm 127:1,
where it mentions
“エホバご自身が
家を建てるのでなければ—”
that ‘unless Jehovah builds the house,
“建てる者たちがそのために骨折って
働いても無駄である”とあります
it’s in vain that his workers
even work hard.’
すべてがスムーズに運ぶのは エホバの
み手と祝福があるおかげなのです
So it’s because of Jehovah’s hand
and his blessing
—that is why everything
runs so smoothly.
What other organization!
このような組織は
ほかには決してありません
No one else can do that
except Jehovah’s people.
It truly is a fine witness
when our young ones
若い人たちが 自分の時間を用いて
心をこめて働く様子は—
wholeheartedly give
of their time.
とても良い証言になっています
Proverbs 20:29 says:
箴言 20章29節にある通り
“若者の美しさはその力”です
“The glory of young men
is their strength.”
And commendably,
you young men and women
若い皆さんは エホバの前で
良い名を得たいと願い—
自分の力を用いておられます
are using your strength
to make a name
with Jehovah.
それは立派なことです
Have you ever considered
helping out in a foreign-language field?
外国語の区域で奉仕したいと
思ったことはありますか？
Perhaps there is a need
in your local circuit.
もしかしたら 今いる巡回区でも
必要があるかもしれません
All over the earth,
わたしたちの目標は 国や人種や
言語を越えて—
the organization
provides language courses
すべての人に 神の言葉から
良いニュースを伝えることです
with the goal of reaching
every nation, tribe, tongue, and people
そのため組織は 世界中で
言語訓練コースを開いています
with the good news of God’s Word.
Brother Juan Carlos Chacón
フアン･カルロス･チャコン兄弟は
エクアドルで急速に拡大している—
serves as a special pioneer
シュワール語の区域で
特別開拓者として奉仕しています
in the rapidly growing Shuar language field
in Ecuador.
He was recently asked to attend
兄弟は最近 地元の支部で開かれる
言語訓練コースに出席しました
a course at the local branch
to become a language teacher
そして教訓者として 言語を学びたい
と願う奉仕者たちを助けました
so that he could help
willing publishers
learn the language.
[Speaking Shuar]
It has been said before,
こう言われたことがあります
“これは悪魔の言葉だ”
“This is a language of the Devil”
—that it should be forgotten.
忘れるべきだ
It serves no purpose.
何の役にも立たない
でも エホバにとって
重要でない国民はいません
But to Jehovah,
no nation is insignificant.
I grew up in an area
of the Ecuadorian jungle
わたしはシュワール族の大集落がある
エクアドルのジャングルで育ちました
where there is
a large community
of Shuar people.
Like many native languages,
多くの土着の言語同様
シュワール語は非常に複雑です
Shuar is very complex.
野外ではもっと多くの働き人が必要です
We need many, many workers in the field.
But if we don’t give them a foundation,
でも 言語の基礎知識を教えて
援助し 励まさなければ—
if we don’t help them
or give them a little push,
この区域に来ることは困難です
it’s difficult for them to enter this field.
I received an invitation to attend
わたしは言語クラスの教訓者の
セミナーに招待されました
a seminar for language instructors.
There were 58 students in the class,
そこには 16の異なった言語グループから
58名の生徒が来ていました
representing 16 different languages
or language groups.
皆さんは革新的に言語を
教える方法を学ぶことになります
わたしたちは実際に効果のある
素晴らしい教え方を学んでいます
We are learning
fantastic teaching techniques,
real techniques that work.
教訓者によると
ユーモアがあれば脳は活性化され—
The instructor told us how humor helps
our minds to create a world of connections,
頭の中で関連付けが
容易になります
which stimulates our brain.
Yeah, I’m like a small child
そうですね
when it comes to drawing.
絵を描くときは小さな子どものようでした
I never learned to draw well.
We draw a scene,
うまく描けませんでしたけど
and starting with our native language
場面を描いて
大きな身振りをしながら—
along with large gestures,
現地語を使います
we act out a dialogue.
場面を演じます
Little by little,
少しづつ新しい言語を使った
場面にしていきます
we convert the scene
into the new language.
よく来られました
今から
出かけてください
What scares me?
不安なことですか？
That I’ve never done this before.
やったことがないんです
This will be my first time.
初めてなんです
I don’t have any experience
teaching languages.
言語を教えた経験がありません
不安でいっぱいですが—
Although I felt intimidated by this,
エホバがおられるなら
すべてのことが可能だと分かっています
I knew that with Jehovah
all things are possible.
シュワール語の言語コースに
皆さんようこそ
Welcome to the first day
of the Shuar language course.
教えられた技術は
道具箱に似ていて—
The techniques they offered us
in the course were like a box of tools
さらに注意深く学び—
that we need to study more carefully
and see how to apply them
それぞれの状況にどう当てはめるかを
理解しなければなりません
in each circumstance.
When we are in the territory,
区域では 人々が神の名前を知ったときに
その目が輝くのを見ることができます
we see how people’s eyes
light up when they learn
the name of God.
Just seeing that there is so much need
for them to learn the truth,
人々は真理を学ぶ必要が大いにあります
それを知るだけでも ここに来て
奉仕を続ける動機が強まります
that has motivated us to come here
and continue serving here.
Since God has created us,
神はわたしたちを造られたので
お見捨てにはなりません
we know that he will
never abandon us.
He thinks about us all the time,
いつもわたしたちのことを考え
愛してくださいます
and he loves us very much.
以前は知りませんでした
I didn’t know that before.
I feel so happy now
本当に神の言葉が理解できて
今は幸せです
because I can really understand
the Word of God.
Being in an isolated group
far from other congregations,
会衆から遠く離れた
孤立した群れにいても—
my wife and I
have felt every day
妻と私はエホバを
毎日身近に感じています
how real Jehovah is.
Jehovah is now looking
今 エホバはこれら小さな群れに
目を留め 注意を払っておられます
and giving his attention
to these small places,
no matter how small they are.
どんなに小さくてもです
If people have a good heart
and want to serve Jehovah,
人々に良い心と神に仕えたい
との願いがあれば—
he will send workers
to give the help that is needed.
エホバは助けるために
働き人を遣わされます
そして わたしたちは本当に
心からエホバにこう申し上げます
And in reality, this moves us
to say to him with all of our heart,
“Thank you, Jehovah.”
“ありがとうございます　エホバ”
There is a lot to do
in Jehovah’s organization
年齢に関係なく エホバの組織の中で
できることはたくさんあります
regardless of our age.
Even if our circumstances
may restrict us,
状況ゆえに できることが
限られているかもしれません
Jehovah sees and values
でも エホバは分かっています
宣教を拡大し
エホバと共に永遠に歩みたいと願い—
all of our efforts
to expand our ministry
and to build
an everlasting future with him.
わたしたちが努力しているのを見て
高く評価してくださいます
Our music video for this month
今月のミュージックビデオが伝えるのは
そのメッセージです
is appropriately entitled
タイトルは—
Building My Future With Jehovah.
“未来を築く エホバと共に” です
どこに向かうか？
At times, I wish I could see
exactly what my future will be
何を選べばいい？
And how my life will turn out
and which road is the right one for me.
この旅路の先に
何が待っている？
でもわかる 確かなことは
But one thing’s for sure,
no matter what comes along,
I live for Jehovah,
to him I belong.
そう エホバのために生きる
Of all the people and things
my life could be filled with,
たとえ何かに 満たされても
忘れない エホバをずっと
The best one of all,
the best one to build with,
喜ばせること 今この手で
Is pleasing Jehovah each day
with the choices I make.
He gave me all that I have;
I’ll never forget it.
どんな小さな輝きでも
ひとつずつ 重ねてゆく
I’m safe in his hands;
I’ll never regret it.
未来をエホバと 築いてゆく
I’m building my future with him
ev’ry step that I take.
時々 出会う
At times, the chance comes along
to take a path I know to be wrong,
“成功って何か？”と
A path that leads me away
from the place that I know I belong.
脚色＜いろづけ＞された明日を 見せられてる
でも揺れない 心に決めた
But keeping in mind
the dedication I made
エホバとの誓い 今も
Can give me the firmness and faith
that won’t fade.
たとえ誰かが 迷わせようと
Of all the people and things
my life could be filled with,
The best one of all,
the best one to build with,
悔やまない 僕らはきっと
夜明けにきらめく 露のように
Is pleasing Jehovah each day
with the choices I make.
He gave me all that I have;
I’ll never forget it.
どんな小さな輝きでも
ひとつずつ 重ねてゆく
I’m safe in his hands;
I’ll never regret it.
未来をエホバと 築いてゆく
I’m building my future with him
ev’ry step that I take.
終わりのない 旅がある
I’m building a future
that never will end
生きてる意味 感じてる
If I build it with help
from Jehovah, my Friend.
そう エホバとの友情に
The happiest moments,
the best life can give,
Come from pleasing Jehovah
each day that I live.
勝るものなど 何もない
たとえ嵐が 押し寄せようと
Of all the people and things
my life could be filled with,
The best one of all,
the best one to build with,
恐れない この先ずっと
岩の上に立つ 家のように
Is pleasing Jehovah each day
with the choices I make.
どんな小さな輝きでも
He gave me all that I have;
I’ll never forget it.
ひとつずつ 重ねてゆく
I’m safe in his hands;
I’ll never regret it.
未来をエホバと 築いてゆく
I’m building my future with him
ev’ry step that I take.
I’m building my future
with him ev’ry step that I take.
未来をエホバと 築いてゆく
An encouraging song indeed!
本当に心が奮い立ちますね！
We encourage all young ones
エホバと共に未来を築きましょう！
to take the message of this program
若い人たちみんなが
今月のプログラムにある—
—to build a future with Jehovah—
このメッセージを
心に留めてくれるよう願っています
to heart.
Prayerfully consider what you can do
エホバに祈って 宣教を拡大するため—
自分には何ができるだろう
と考えてみてください
to expand your ministry.
Always safeguard
your most valuable possession
あなたが持つ一番大切なもの—
—your precious relationship
with Jehovah.
エホバとの友情—
それをしっかりと
守り続けてください
Never forget
that there are more with you
たくさんの敵がいます
でも もっとたくさんの友がいることを
決して忘れないでください
than there are against you.
It is true that Satan, the demons,
敵は サタン 悪霊 この世です
and this world are against you.
では あなたの側にはだれがいますか？
But your brothers and sisters,
including the Governing Body,
are with you;
兄弟たち 姉妹たち—
統治体が共にいます
the angels are with you;
天使たちも共にいます
復活して 不滅性を与えられている
油そそがれた人たちも共にいます
the resurrected immortal anointed ones
are with you;
Jesus is with you;
イエスがあなたと一緒です
and most important,
Jehovah is with you.
そして エホバがあなたのそばに
おられるのです
みんながそばにいることを
決して忘れないでください
You are never alone!
To conclude,
we have greetings
to share with you
プログラムの最後に
昨年4月フランスのパリで開かれた—
from the special convention
that was held
特別大会からのあいさつを
お伝えしたいと思います
in July of last year
in Paris, France.
I had the privilege
of attending this convention
教育委員会の援助者
ケニス･フローディン兄弟と共に—
with Brother Kenneth Flodin,
この大会に出席することができました
a helper to the Teaching Committee.
While most of the convention program
was in French,
プログラムのほとんどは
フランス語で提供されましたが—
it was simultaneously interpreted
世界中から来た代表者たちのため—
into Croatian, English,
プログラムはクロアチア語 英語
ポーランド語に同時通訳されました
and Polish
for the benefit
of the international delegates.
You will be happy to know
この大会で 71人の姉妹たちと
41人の兄弟たちが—
that 71 new sisters
and 41 new brothers
エホバへの献身を表わして
水のバプテスマを受けました
symbolized their dedication
through water baptism.
うれしいですね
最年長は80歳の姉妹
最年少は10歳でした
The oldest baptismal candidate
was an 80-year-old sister
and the youngest
was a 10-year-old.
The young candidates
had to overcome
若い兄弟姉妹たちは
バプテスマを受けるまでに—
various challenges in order
to reach their goal
いろいろな問題を乗り越えてきました
of baptism.
4人の兄弟姉妹は 両親とも
エホバの証人ではない中で—
Four of them took this step
even though their parents
are not Jehovah’s Witnesses.
多くの若い人たちは 学校での圧力を
受けながら進歩してきました
Many of these dear young ones
had to overcome
peer pressure at school
—pressure to do things
エホバが喜ばれないことを
させようとする圧力です
Jehovah does not like.
2人の若い実の兄弟がいました
Two of the young brothers,
also fleshly brothers,
兄弟たちは以前
暴力的なゲームをしていたようです
used to play
violent video games.
Through their personal Bible study
でも 聖書を研究し
個人的な関心を示してもらううちに—
and the personal interest
shown in them,
they came to understand
Jehovah’s viewpoint on violence
エホバが暴力を
どう見ているかが分かり—
and made the necessary changes
to progress spiritually.
エホバとの関係を成長させようと
生活を調整しました
By taking this first step
バプテスマという最初のステップを
踏むことで 兄弟たちは—
of getting baptized,
these brothers and sisters have shown
that they want to build a future
エホバと共に将来を築きたいと
願っていることを示しました
with Jehovah.
Let us all do everything
エホバとの友情を成長させてゆくため
ベストを尽くしましょう
we can to continue making
spiritual progress,
そうすれば エホバは是認し
ほほえんでくださいます
which will bring
Jehovah’s smile of approval.
兄弟姉妹たち
皆さんを心から愛しています
Brothers and sisters,
we love you very much.
エホバの証人の世界本部からお送りした
JW Broadcastingでした
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.